Guide to the Daniel B. Krinsley geology of Iran and the arctic collection, 1932-1999 MS2171
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Daniel B. Krinsley geology of Iran and the arctic collection
1932-1999
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Krinsley, Daniel B.
MS2171
7.5 Linear Feet
The material in the collection concerns the geology of Iran and the geology of arctic regions including Alasaka, Greenland, and Canada. Dr. Daniel B. Krinsley conducted geological field studies in Iran in the 1960s and 1970s. The bulk of the first series is comprised of photographs, ERTS images, and air photographs of the playas of Iran. A playas is a desert basin with no outlet which periodically fills with water to form a temporary lake. The first series also includes research files, color images and negatives, and articles written by and gathered by Dr. Krinsley, who was Chief of the Environmental imapact analysis program for the U.S. Geological Survey. The material dates from 1932-1999. The collection also includes maps, geographic surveys, journals articles and studies, and other publications concerning the geology of arctic regions and Iran.
Scope and Contents
The material in the collection concerns the geology of Iran and the geology of arctic regions including Alasaka, Greenland, and Canada. Dr. Daniel B. Krinsley conducted geological field studies in Iran in the 1960s and 1970s. The bulk of the first series is comprised of photographs, ERTS images, and air photographs of the playas of Iran. A playas is a desert basin with no outlet which periodically fills with water to form a temporary lake. The first series also includes research files, color images and negatives, and articles written by and gathered by Dr. Krinsley. The collection also includes maps, geographic surveys, journals articles and studies, and other publications concerning the geology of arctic regions and Iran. The material dates from 1932-1999.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Series 1: Gift of Dr. Daniel B. Krinsley, 1990. Series 2 and 3: Gift of Dr. Daniel B. Krinsley, 2012 August 3, (Accession 2012.067)
Biography
Daniel B. Krinsley was Chief of the Environmental imapact analysis program for the U.S. Geological Survey. In 1983, Krinsley was awarded the Distinguished Service Award by the Department of Interior for his pioneering research in geomorpholigic and geologic research in previously little known areas in Alaska, Greenland, and Iran.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Geology of Iran [original donation], Arctic geology, and Iran geology.
Separated Materials
The following publications were cataloged and added to the Special Collections book collection. Each record has a note indicating gift of Daniel Krinsley.
100 questions about Iran Across the Great Deserts Persepolis Pasargadae Iran Facts & Figures Iran by Aziz Hatami Aron of Kangeq by Eigil Knuth Iran (1971 by Ministry of Information) Parade of Persepolis
Geology -- Iran; Geology; Iran; Playas
- Geology of Iran [original donation], 1950-1972; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Organized into 3 subseries: Photographs, Subject files, Publications.
  Scope and Contents
  The series is comprised of photographs, ERTS images, and air photographs of the playas of Iran. A playas is a desert basin with no outlet which periodically fills with water to form a temporary lake. The first series also includes research files, color images and negatives, and articles written by and gathered by Dr. Krinsley. The collection also includes maps, geographic surveys, journals articles and studies, and other publications concerning the geology of arctic regions and Iran. The material dates from 1950-1972.
  - Photographs, 1965-1972; Series 1 Subseries 1
    Original order retained.
    - Iran 1965 Playas Rolls 1,2,3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Iran 1965 Playas Rolls 4,5,6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Iran 1966 Playas (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Iran 1972 Playas Photos 1-85 [1/2] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Iran 1972 Playas Photos 1-85 [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Iran 1967 Playas Rolls 1,2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Iran 1967 Playas Rolls 3,4 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Iran 1967 Playas Rolls 5,6 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Iran 1967 Playas Rolls 7 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subject files, 1950 - Circa 1970; Series 1 Subseries 2
    Original order retained. Loosely alphabetical.
    - Subject files: Late Pleistocene Climate of Iran, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Subject files: Iran Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Subject files: Climate, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - subject files: ERTS Coverage index, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - subject files: ERTS Reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - subject files: ERTS-1 Symposium paper G18 U.S. Geological Survey-Ori, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - subject files: Fauna Iran, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - subject files: Great Kavir Road -ENG. Soils, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - subject files: History - Current Events, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - subject files: Index Maps, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - subject files: Damghan, Sabsevar, Great Kavir, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - subject files: Completed machanical analysis, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - subject files: Machanical analysis, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - subject files: Maps, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - subject files: Photo Index, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - subject files: Physical Setting, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - subject files: Playa Summary, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - subject files: Pleistocene - Iran (Near East), undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - subject files: Qanats, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - subject files: Playas References General Classifications, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - subject files: Iranian Report Acknowledgements:, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - subject files: Monthly River Discharge, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - subject files: Soil Samples, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - subject files: Stone Tools, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - subject files: Tourtelot Analysis, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - subject files: Transliterations of Farsi, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - subject files: Iran - Travel, Documentation, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - subject files: Tree Ring Data, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - subject files: Vegetation, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - subject files: Archaeology Iran, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - subject files: AAG Iran Photo Exhibit, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - subject files: Summary of the Utilization of ERTS-1 generaged images... by Daniel B. Krinsley, 1974 October (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - subject files: Altitudes, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - subject files: Paper ERTS-1 Generated Images in the Evaluation of Some Iranian Playas as Sites for Economic and Engr., undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - subject files: Zagros Playa transparencies, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - subject files: Zagros Playa color images, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - subject files: Monitoring water resources in Qom Playa, West-Central Iran, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - subject files: Iran ERTS, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - subject files: Iran ERTS report color negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - subject files: Tree Rings Iran, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - subject files: ERTS-1 Indices of Iran, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - subject files: Publications by Daniel B. Krinsley, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - subject files: Landscape photos of Middle Asia and Central Asia, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Publications, 1970 and undated; Series 1 Subseries 3
    - A Geomorphological and Paleoclimatological Study of the Playas of Iran Part I, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - A Geomorphological and Paleoclimatological Study of the Playas of Iran Part II, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Publication translations [1/3], undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Publication translations [2/3], undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Publication translations [3/3], undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Arctic geology, 1940-1980; Series 2
  Organized into three subseries: Maps, Journals and studies, Other publications
  This series contains materials regarding the geology of Arctic regions including Alasaka, Greenland, and Canada. The materials include maps, academic journals, geographic surveys and studies, military field manuals, and other publications. The materials range in date from 1940-1980.
  - Maps, 1961-2009; 1961-1965; Series 2 Subseries 1
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Atlas of Arctic Environment, 1961; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Defense Intelligence Agency: Terrain Study of Alaska Part VIII, 1964; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Department of the Interior, United States Geological Survey Map Showing Extent of Glaciations in Alaska, 1965; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - National Geographic: Arctic Ocean, 2009; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Journals and studies, 1928-1981; Series 2 Subseries 2
    - Arctic Earth Science Investigations, Centrum So, Northeast Greenland, 1960; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - The Arctic: Last Unmanaged Frontier, 1981; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bog Flats and Physiographic Processes in the Upper Kuskokwin Rover Region, AK, 1956; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Bulletin of the Geological Society of America, 1949; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Canada Department of Mines and Technical Surveys - Geological Survey of Canada, 1952-1958; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences, 1970; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - The Drawings and Watercolors by Rear-Admiral Frederick William Beechey, 1980; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Exploratory Study of the Principal Soil Groups of Alaska, 1951; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Flora of Alaska and Adjacent Parts of Canada, 1943-1946; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Geological Survey of Canada, 1969; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Geology of the North Star Bugt Area Northwest Greenland, 1963; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - The Geography of the Polar Regions, 1928; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Glacial Geology Across the Crest of the Sierra Nevada, California, 1964; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Glaciation of the Alps - University of Colorado Studies, 1968; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Headquarters Quartermaster Research and Engineering Command US Army: Atlas of Mountain Glaciers in the Northern Hemisphere, 1958; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Landscape of Northern Greenland, 1972; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Man Living in the Arctic, 1960; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Permafrost, by Geological Survey U.S. Department of the Interior, 1945; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Photo Interpretation of the Terrain along the Southern Part of the Alaska Highway, 1945-1946; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Physiographic Divisions of Alaska, 1965; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Quarternary Geology of the Mount Chamberlin Area Brooks Range, Alaska, 1965; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Report on Operation Groundhog North Greenland, 1957-1958; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Some Aspects of Glaciers and Glaciology, 1956; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Terrain Study of the Exercise Great Bear Area, Tanana Valley, Alaska, 1961; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Terrain Study of the Exercise Great Bear Area, Tanana Valley, Alaska, 1961; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Vegetation of Northwestern North America as an Aid in Interpretation of Geologic Data, 1958; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Wissenschaftliche Ergebnisse der Finnishen Expedition nach Patagonien..., 1965; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Wissenschaftliche Ergebnisse der Finnishen Expedition nach Patagonien..., 1970; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Other publications, 1914-1996; 1950-1970; Series 2 Subseries 3
    - Department of the Army Technical Manual: Geology and Its Military Applications, 1952; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Department of the Army Field Manual: Mountain Operations, 1959; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Department of the Army Field Manual: Survival, 1957; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Engineer Intelligence Guide: Glossary of Natural Terrain Features, 1957; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Engineer Intelligence Guide: Production of Cross-Country Movement Studies, 1959; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Frozen Ground: The News Bulletin of the International Permafrost Association, 1994-1996; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Greenland, 1971; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - The Hurley Collection - Antarctica, 1914-1917; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - National Geographic: Alaska, 1956-1972; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Pocket Guide to Alaska Trees, 1950; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Iran geology, 1932-1999; 1950-1980; Series 3
  Organized into three subseries: Maps, Journals and studies, Other publications.
  This series contains materials regarding the geology of Iran. The materials include maps, academic journals, geographic surveys and studies, magazines, and other publications. The materials range in date from 1932-1999, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1950-1980.
  - Maps, 1952-1970; Series 3 Subseries 1
    - Afghanistan, China, Iran, Jammu and Kasmir, Pakistan, USSR, 1966; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Afghanistan, Iran, Muscat and Oman, Pakistan, Trucial States, 1970; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Elburz Mountains, 1963; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Etude Geographique de la Mer Caspienne, 1969; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Gulf of Oman, 1964; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Iran Highway Map, 1966; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Iran, Iraq, USSR, 1968; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground), 1969; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - La Baie de Pahlavi (Amzali) (Etude Physique), 1969; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Les principles rivieres de la region de Guilan, 1969; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Persian Gulf, 1963; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - USAF Aeronautical Approach Chart, 1952; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - World Road Maps: Iran, Afghanistan, USSR (and vicinity), 1962; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - World Road Maps: Iran, Iraq, Saudia Arabia, Kuwait (and vicinity), 1962; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - World Road Maps: Iran, Iraqu, Turkey, USSR (and vicinity), 1962; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Journals and studies, 1959-1979; Series 3 Subseries 2
    - Air Force Cambridge Research Laboratories: The Salt Deserts of Iran as Climatic Evidence, 1967; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Annals of the Association of American Geographers, 1979; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Arid Zone Research Centre Publications, 1959-1960; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Geological Survey of Iran: Geological Observations on Alluvial Deposits in Northern Iran, 1966; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Geological Survey of Iran: Geology and Petrography of Mt. Damavand and its Environment (Central Alborz), Iran, 1970; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Geological Survey of Iran: Preliminary Metallogenic Map of Iran, 1965; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Geological Survey of Iran: Revieu of the Geology of Iran, 1971; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Geologie und Hydrogeologie des Gebietes von Kashan/Iran, 1972; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - A Geomorphological and Paleoclimatological Study of the Playas of Iran, 1970; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - The Prehistory of Southwestern Iran: A Preliminary Report, 1967; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - A Review of the Structural History and Tectonics of Iran, 1965; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Technical Cooperation with Iran, 1972; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Tubinger Geographische Studien, 1971; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - The Utilization of Erts - Part 1 and 2, 1974; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - The Utilization of Erts - Summary, 1974; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Wurzburger Geographische Arbieten, 1974; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Other publications, 1932-1999; 1960-1980; Series 3 Suberies 3
    - Basic Facts About Iran, undated; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - GSA Today: Middle East Tectonics, 1997; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Iran, undated; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Iran National Tourist Organization pamphlet, undated; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Joods Historisch Museum: summary, undated; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - National Geographic re: Iran, 1975-1999; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Publications in Persian, 1932-1933; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      General
      This folder contains two publications written in Persian. One is a booklet published in 1933 by the National Geographic Organization that discusses Iranian geography. The other is an edition of a popular Persian magazine called Maktab Pars, published in 1932.
    - Shiraz, undated; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - A Short Guide to Persepolis, 1963; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - TIME: Iran in Turmoil, 1978; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Transliteration of Farsi Geographic Names to Latin Alphabet, 1966; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - The Unesco Courier: Iran; Cultural Crossroads for 2,500 Years, 1971; Series 3 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 8)